<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached on the 30th of January, 1684, the day of martyrdom of King Charles I, of blessed memory by Edward Pelling ...</title>
            <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53972</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1097</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23219</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12755743</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12755743</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93420</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53972)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93420)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 727:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached on the 30th of January, 1684, the day of martyrdom of King Charles I, of blessed memory by Edward Pelling ...</title>
                  <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T.M., and are to be sold by Randal Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXXXVII, 1 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93420:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93420:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached on The 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>January,</hi> 1684. The Day of MARTYRDOM OF King Charles Of Bleſſed Memory.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>EDWARD PELLING,</hi> Chaplain to His Grace the Duke of <hi>Somerſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>T. M.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Randal Taylor</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall.</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:93420:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93420:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSAL. 137. 1.</bibl>
               <q>By the Rivers of <hi>Babylon</hi> there we ſat down, yea we wept, when we remembred <hi>Zion.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THeſe Words do manifeſtly relate to the Captive-condition of the <hi>Jews,</hi> after that Remarkable Overthrow of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when that Cruel and Barbarous Enemy the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> (called expreſly, <hi>the Rod of God's Anger, Iſa.</hi> 10.) had now taken the City, burnt the Temple, conſumed and diſmantled the whole Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolis, ſlain the Nobles, and ſeized the Perſon of their King <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> and ſo carried Him and his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects away Captives to <hi>Babylon,</hi> (that is, into a Land of <hi>Confuſion,</hi> ſo called from the Confuſion of <hi>Languages</hi> in thoſe Parts) there to ſmart a long time for their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrigibleneſs and Wantonneſs at home; that they might Reflect upon their Folly, and learn to value their Former Felicities by the <hi>Loſs</hi> of them: the <hi>onely</hi> Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, that can effectually teach thoſe Obſtinate and Ungrateful Wretches, that will not learn to be Wiſe at the Coſt of their <hi>Anceſtors</hi> Experience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By the Rivers of</hi> Babylon, <hi>there they ſat down;</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93420:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
from any Towns, or Cities, (ſaith S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>) to ſpend part of their time (as ſome conceive) in drain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Marſhes, and to <hi>keep</hi> away the Reſt; and ſo between Labour and Sorrow, to wear out that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Life, for which they had made ſuch a woful Exchange.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There</hi> they wept (when 'twas too late) at the ſad remembrance of <hi>Zion;</hi> that is, at the thoughts of that Proſperous and Flouriſhing Condition, which once they Enjoyed, but were now Deprived of, both in Church and State. For Mount <hi>Sion</hi> was the Principal Place both for the Exerciſes of <hi>Religion,</hi> and for the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of <hi>Juſtice.</hi> There ſtood the Temple of God, and <hi>thither the Tribes went up, the Tribes of the Lord, unto the Teſtimony of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>to give thanks unto the Name of the Lord,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122. 4. And (that God and his Anointed might dwell together) there alſo <hi>were ſet the Thrones of Judgment, the Thrones of the Houſe of</hi> David, as it is <hi>ver.</hi> 5. Admirable was the Conſtitution of the <hi>Jews</hi> State; and they the Happieſt of all Nations, as well in Sacred as in Civil reſpects, till they Surfeited themſelves with Abundance of Proſperity, and were ſo Intoxicated with it under their own Vines and Figtrees, that they forgat both the Author, and Inſtruments of their Happineſs.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Story,</hi> is of <hi>Them:</hi> the <hi>Application</hi> of it, is for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s;</hi> and at the very firſt view we may eaſily accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate this ſad Text to this ſadder Day. For, do but Date the Captivity, <hi>Stylo Novo:</hi> inſtead of, <hi>By the Rivers of Babylon,</hi> read, <hi>In a Land of Confuſion,</hi> (a <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi> in our own Countrey:) Shift you Pious Thoughts from the Monarch of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to the Memory of our Own Soveraign, a Greater, a Better than <hi>Zedekiah,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93420:3"/>
(the Mirrour of Princes, the Nobleſt of Martyrs, the Wonder of Ages, and the Honour of Men:) Lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your Eyes (if yet ye can Endure to behold) the Scaffold, the Ax, the Block, and all that Pageantry of Oppreſſion, which the Sun never before beheld provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in that Manner, and with thoſe Circumſtances, for a <hi>Crowned</hi> Head? Conſider with what Pomp of Inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity that Mighty Prince fell, how Three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms fell with Him, how He was buried in the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines both of Church and State, as in the Ruines of a Shattered World: Remember thoſe manifold Miſeries that were <hi>throughout;</hi> ſome, the <hi>Praeface;</hi> others, the <hi>Epilogue</hi> to the diſmal Tragoedy of this Day; and then tell me, wherein Our Captivity differ'd from that in the Text, unleſs it did in This, that 'twas more Infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and Reproachful, becauſe at Home; and 'twas not (God be Bleſſed) for Seventy years; 'twas not ſo Laſting as Our Sins; the Deliverance out of it was too Quick and Haſty for the Repentance of thoſe Miſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants who made us Captives.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not therefore take much notice of the Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Condition of the <hi>Jews,</hi> it being a matter of <hi>Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign</hi> conſideration; but apply my ſelf wholly to the Buſineſs of the Day. And in the proſecution of it, 1. I ſhall firſt give you ſome account of thoſe Miſeries which were the Attendants of Our Captivity; and then, 2. Shall, in the ſecond place, try if it be poſſible for me to perſuade Men, not to be ſo Improvident again, as to ſuffer themſelves to be made Captives the <hi>Second</hi> time; but to Beware in <hi>Time,</hi> and to bethink themſelves before it be too <hi>Late,</hi> before they groan again under ſuch another State of Bondage.</p>
            <p>1. Firſt then; That which was the principal <hi>Cauſe,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:93420:4"/>
or at leaſt the greateſt <hi>Ingredient</hi> of all the Miſeries of the <hi>Jews,</hi> was the Captive-condition of their <hi>King.</hi> This they particularly lamented, that <hi>ſuch as had been brought up in Scarlet, did now embrace Dunghills;</hi> that <hi>their King and their Princes were in the hands of the Gentiles;</hi> that <hi>the Crown was fallen from their Head;</hi> that <hi>the Breath of their Noſtrils, the Anointed of the Lord, was taken in the Pits,</hi> as you find in ſeveral pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the <hi>Lamentations</hi> of <hi>Jeremiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what elſe was the Undermining and Subverting of <hi>Our</hi> King's Throne, but an effectual Stratagem to overthrow the Proſperity of the whole <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and to let in that huge Army of Miſeries, which for many years made us not onely the moſt <hi>Calamitous,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the moſt <hi>Contemptible</hi> and <hi>Infamous</hi> Nation under Heaven? He that carefully reads the Shameful Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of thoſe Times, will find, that all thoſe Evils which were heaped up upon the Head of our <hi>Prince,</hi> fell down upon our <hi>own</hi> Pates. Though He <hi>Felt</hi> the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, yet we <hi>Sunk</hi> and <hi>Periſh'd</hi> under the weight of it. Every Wound which <hi>Majeſty</hi> received, did help to let out the Blood and Spirits of the <hi>Subject</hi> too; nor was it poſſible to Preſerve the Welfare of the Body Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, by Weakning and Impairing Him, who was the Common Life of the Three Kingdoms. Thoſe Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial and Long-ſtudied Methods which were uſed to Leſſen His Authority, to Profane His Honour, to Spoil Him of His Peace, (of all but the Peace of His <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> and almoſt of <hi>That</hi> too) to Strip Him of His Prerogatives, and at laſt to Deſtroy His Sacred Life; theſe Methods, I ſay, were the Inſtruments not more of <hi>His,</hi> than of our <hi>own</hi> Ruine; and as <hi>He</hi> fell and died by degrees, ſo did the whole <hi>Nation</hi> gradually
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93420:4"/>
Languiſh, and fall into the Pangs of Death with Him. Happy had this Land been for many Ages under the Succeſſive Government of <hi>Kings,</hi> eſpecially of ſuch as were <hi>Good;</hi> and none could be ever <hi>Better</hi> than <hi>This.</hi> Under the Shadow of His Wings we did Rejoice, till His Feathers were clipp'd: Peace and Plenty was our Portion; and every Man was Eaſie in his Cottage, as long as He ſat Eaſie in the Throne: Our <hi>Liberties</hi> were Secure; our <hi>Laws</hi> had Life; and <hi>Religion,</hi> which Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alteth a Nation, never flouriſh'd more in This, as long as he enjoyed the <hi>Prerogatives</hi> which are juſtly due to the <hi>Head</hi> of the Church. No ſooner was His <hi>Honour</hi> touched, but our <hi>Faelicity</hi> was invaded too; eſpecially when Wickedneſs was ſo Impudent as to draw the <hi>Sword</hi> upon Him, and to thruſt at Him with the Point. Our <hi>Happineſs</hi> Declined as His <hi>Peace</hi> did: it kept even pace with our Prince His Fortune; the more ſtill That tended to Ruine, the Faſter He was Hunted to the Scaffold; and then it Expired (though in hope of a Reſurrection) when He laid down His Sacred Neck, and died a Martyr for Religion, and a Victim for His People. Great were the Miſeries that attended that Unnatural and Deviliſh Rebellion; but as long as the <hi>King</hi> was Safe, the Calamities were the leſs felt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there was a Proſpect of Reparation; at leaſt, of a ſpeedy <hi>End</hi> of them. Though that Rebellious Faction in Parliament purſued Him like a <hi>Partridge upon the Mountains,</hi> yet we did not give all for <hi>loſt,</hi> becauſe they <hi>Declared, Promiſed, Proteſted,</hi> and <hi>Swore</hi> by all that is Great and Sacred, that they intended not to Hurt His <hi>Perſon,</hi> nor to Invade His Juſt <hi>Rights.</hi> Throughout that Bloody War, there was <hi>ſomething</hi> ſtill to <hi>allay</hi> our Pains, becauſe we hoped that the Wounds in our Sides
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93420:5"/>
were not <hi>Mortal.</hi> Nay, though truſting to Mens <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions,</hi> He threw himſelf into the Hands of thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidious Villains who afterwards ſet a Price upon <hi>His</hi> Blood, as <hi>Judas</hi> did upon our <hi>Saviour's,</hi> yet the King <hi>Himſelf</hi> did not yet <hi>Deſpair,</hi> becauſe thoſe Men had vowed in a <hi>Solemn League and Covenant of their own,</hi> and with Hands lifted up to the moſt High God, That they would Preſerve His Perſon, Crown, and Dignity. Nay, when thoſe <hi>Iſcariots</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> had bought Him for 200000 Pounds, and <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and the reſt of thoſe True-Proteſtant <hi>Janizaries,</hi> had gotten Him in their Clutches, though there was reaſon enough for our Hearts to <hi>Sink</hi> and <hi>Fail</hi> us, the King Himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now actually a <hi>Captive,</hi> and Loyalty and Religion in Captivity <hi>with</hi> Him; yet ſuch were the Solemn <hi>Profeſſions</hi> and <hi>Proteſtations</hi> of thoſe Men, of <hi>Further Addreſſes</hi> to His Majeſty, and of <hi>Perſonal Treaties</hi> with Him, that we were ſtill willing to <hi>hope,</hi> that <hi>yet</hi> we ſhould not ſit down by the Rivers of <hi>Babel,</hi> to weep there. Once more; When the Conſpirators carried Him <hi>away,</hi> firſt to <hi>Holmeby,</hi> thence to <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> and thence conveyed Him to the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> though we <hi>fear'd,</hi> that all their Treaties were nothing but <hi>Pretence</hi> and <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> to blind Mens Eyes; though they uſed Majeſty with ſuch Indignities as none, but that Prince, could have born; though ſome of the Faction did now ſay openly, That the King was no more than a <hi>Dead Dog;</hi> though every diſcerning Man apprehended that the King's Life was now upon the very <hi>brink</hi> of Deſtruction; yet even <hi>then</hi> were we wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to hope that all our Happineſs was not yet come to a <hi>full</hi> Period; becauſe the <hi>Majority</hi> of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, enraged at <hi>laſt</hi> to ſee how they had been cheated,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93420:5"/>
and out of a juſt Abhorrence of the intended Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, voted, That <hi>the King's Conceſſions were Satisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and Sufficient Grounds for Peace.</hi> But when once we ſaw thoſe Men barred out of the Houſe ſuddenly after; when once we ſaw that Curſed Vote of the Remaining Faction, <hi>That the King had taken Arms againſt the Parliament, and was guilty of all the Blood which had been ſhed in the War, and therefore ought to expiate the Crime with His own Blood;</hi> when once we ſaw a Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natick Army, that had been uſed to Blood, ſo Thirſty for more, that nothing would ſatisfie them, but Blood <hi>Royal;</hi> when once we ſaw a <hi>Tribunal</hi> Erected, and ſome of the <hi>Legion</hi> of <hi>Hell</hi> Sitting on it, and a Judge appointed, whoſe moſt <hi>Honourable</hi> Character is, that he was <hi>Pontius Pilate the Second;</hi> when once we ſaw Majeſty treated there with ſuch Barbarouſneſs and Contempt, and thence carried through Smoke, Spit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and Flouts, (ſome of them ſuch as were uſed at the Condemnation of the Holy <hi>Jeſus;</hi>) when we ſaw Him led like a Lamb to be Slaughter'd on a Scaffold at His Palace Door; when we ſaw, that as the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian</hi> had clipp'd off His <hi>Locks,</hi> ſo the <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> had now cut off His <hi>Head;</hi> when the <hi>one</hi> Faction had Deſtroyed the <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>other</hi> had now mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd the <hi>Man;</hi> Then, then our Hopes were <hi>gone,</hi> and we could not but conclude our ſelves a <hi>Loſt,</hi> a <hi>Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated,</hi> an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndone</hi> People: And while Some were ſo Barbarous, as even to <hi>waſh their Hands</hi> in that Bleſſed Martyr's Blood, the whole Nation was taught to make <hi>This</hi> Uſe of the Shedding of it, That if ever it ſhould pleaſe God, after the Death of the <hi>Father,</hi> to Reſtore the <hi>Son,</hi> it would be our <hi>Beſt Policy</hi> to be moſt <hi>Tender</hi> not of His <hi>Life</hi> onely, but of His <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:93420:6"/>
too; it being Impoſſible ſo to ſever <hi>His</hi> Intereſt from our <hi>Own,</hi> but that of neceſſity we muſt Stand or Fall <hi>with</hi> Him: <hi>Every</hi> Man's Welfare is ſo wrapped up in <hi>His,</hi> that we muſt take ſome Share in His Fortune, whether it be a Crown of <hi>Gold,</hi> or of <hi>Thorns,</hi> that He wears upon His Head.</p>
            <p>2. The King being deſtroyed, the Miſeries which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> are not to be written fully, but in another Book of Martyrs.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Church,</hi> our Calamities were ſuch, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever had a reſpect for <hi>Conſcience,</hi> for <hi>Religion,</hi> for a <hi>God,</hi> could not but be deeply afflicted, to ſee what <hi>Contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melies</hi> were thrown upon every thing that was <hi>Sacred.</hi> Indeed the <hi>Churches</hi> Sufferings <hi>began,</hi> when the <hi>Kings</hi> Troubles Commenced, and ſo <hi>Increaſed,</hi> as <hi>They</hi> did; becauſe Traitors ſaw, that the <hi>Doctrine, Diſcipline,</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> were ſuch Pillars of <hi>State</hi> too, that 'twas Impoſſible for them to Pull down or Reach the <hi>Crown,</hi> but by ſtepping firſt upon the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines of <hi>Prelacy,</hi> and all <hi>Order</hi> in <hi>Religion.</hi> And if we may have leave to make ſome little Obſervations, 'tis ſomewhat Remarkable, That firſt the <hi>Primate,</hi> and four years after, the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> were <hi>both</hi> Murder'd in the <hi>ſame</hi> Month; the one on the Tenth, the other on the Thirtieth of <hi>January;</hi> that Great <hi>Prelate</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his <hi>Prince</hi> the way that even <hi>He</hi> was to go too, (ſomewhat like <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> that was the <hi>Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his <hi>Sufferings,</hi> as well as <hi>Birth,</hi> and prepared the way for the Prince of Peace, not onely into the <hi>World,</hi> but to the <hi>Croſs</hi> alſo.) <hi>Monarchy</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> to the Grave; and <hi>Religion,</hi> that was the <hi>Mourner,</hi> dropp'd in at laſt. Good God! What <hi>Variety</hi> of Sects had we, that Martyr'd the very <hi>Creed;</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:93420:6"/>
ſo that ſome even of the <hi>Faction</hi> did confeſs, that upon the diſſolution of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> more <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>Haereſies</hi> preſently ſtarted up, than ever were <hi>heard</hi> of among us before, under that Government which was Decried as <hi>Antichriſtian?</hi> And all theſe Sects were either <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred,</hi> or <hi>Encourag'd</hi> by thoſe Rebels, who by <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> the Nation into a great many weak <hi>Parties,</hi> ſtrengthned their own <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations,</hi> and made <hi>each</hi> Party both Unable to <hi>Riſe,</hi> and Afraid to <hi>Mutter</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Common Oppreſſions. We had the <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,</hi> the <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> the <hi>Fifth-Monarchiſt,</hi> the <hi>Browniſt,</hi> the <hi>Quaker,</hi> the <hi>Seeker,</hi> the <hi>Ranter,</hi> the <hi>Adamite,</hi> nay the very <hi>Atheiſt</hi> himſelf for Company; and all theſe the Natural <hi>Spawn</hi> of the <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> that Prolifick and Unruly <hi>Leviathan,</hi> that not content to have taken his Paſtime in the <hi>Lemain Lake,</hi> hath troubled the Waters in all Parts of the Chriſtian World. So many <hi>Sects</hi> as there were, ſo many <hi>Plagues</hi> there were in this little Iſland; and what could we expect would be the <hi>Iſſue</hi> of this <hi>Complication</hi> of Unhappineſſes, but that the Intereſt of Religion would be weakned, and its Reputation rendred Contemptible; ſo many Bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fac'd Enemies being Allowed and Encouraged to fall Foul upon the <hi>Church,</hi> purſuant to that Baſe <hi>Example</hi> which was given them by a moſt Unconſcionable Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament? <hi>Biſhops</hi> were ready to be torn in pieces, as the Limbs of <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> Multitudes of the <hi>Inferiour</hi> Clergy had no other Rewards for all their Labours and Fidelity in the Service of Chriſt, but <hi>Sequeſtrations, Impriſonment,</hi> and all manner of <hi>Cruelties,</hi> beyond the Tyranny even of a <hi>True-Proteſtant Grand Seignior.</hi> The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities</hi> were corrupted with Haereſie and Hypocriſie, the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Devil having taken his Work out of his
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93420:7"/>
Hands, by ſowing themſelves ſuch Tares and Cockle in the Seminaries of Religion, as in a little time would have deſtroyed the very Life and Being of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, had not God himſelf been the Husbandman. The <hi>Liturgy,</hi> which they ſolemnly Proteſted that they would onely <hi>Reform,</hi> was ſoon thrown out of doors, to make room for <hi>Blaſphemies,</hi> and <hi>Enthuſiaſm,</hi> which made the Worſhip of God an <hi>Abomination. Pulpits,</hi> that were erected for the <hi>Sons of the Prophets,</hi> were made the <hi>Trading</hi> places of <hi>Mechanicks</hi> and the <hi>Baſeſt</hi> of the People, who were onely skilful in Cheating Men of their Money; and ſuch another Famine was in the Church, as was once in <hi>Samaria,</hi> when every <hi>Aſſes Head</hi> was ſold for Fourſcore pieces of Silver. <hi>Sacraments</hi> were neglected, and almoſt given over, and the People were ſo Frighted and Diſcouraged from their Duty, that in ſome Places of the Kingdom the Holy Communion was not uſed for almoſt Twenty years together: <hi>A Glorious and Bleſſed Reformation!</hi> Thoſe <hi>Lands</hi> which the Piety of our Anceſtors had ſo ſolemnly ſet apart for the Encouragement of <hi>Learning,</hi> and for the Edification of Souls, were made the Price of <hi>Rebellion</hi> and Blood, and a Booty for the moſt <hi>Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and Perjur'd</hi> Villains upon the Earth. <hi>Truth, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, Juſtice, Obedience, Love,</hi> and other the <hi>Eſſential</hi> Parts of Religion, were all Trampled under foot: and when <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Worſhip</hi> were thus Scandalouſly Diſhonoured, I do not wonder that ſome of God's <hi>Houſes</hi> were Filthily Polluted too: When the <hi>Creed</hi> was Contaminated, when the <hi>Lords Prayer</hi> was De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, when the <hi>Decalogue</hi> in all its Parts was Broken, when the Orthodox <hi>Miniſtry</hi> was Caſhier'd, when <hi>Fonts</hi> and <hi>Altars</hi> were Defiled, and when the <hi>Church</hi> was
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93420:7"/>
               <hi>Plunder'd</hi> and <hi>Stripp'd</hi> within and without, it is no marvel that many <hi>Oratories</hi> were ſo Profaned too, as to be Turn'd at laſt into <hi>Stables</hi> for <hi>Horſes,</hi> by thoſe <hi>Beaſts of the People,</hi> that before had made them Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aries for <hi>Traytors,</hi> Nurſeries of <hi>Rebels</hi> and <hi>Regicides,</hi> and <hi>Dens of Thieves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. Well might we <hi>Weep,</hi> when we remembred <hi>Sion,</hi> whoſe <hi>ways did now mourn, becauſe her Children could not come to her Solemn Feaſt her Gates were deſolate, her Prieſts ſighed, her Virgins were afflicted, her Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was departed, her Princes were purſued like Harts, her Perſecutors overtook her, her Enemies Proſper'd, and ſhe her ſelf was in Bitterneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> as the Prophet ſpake, <hi>Lam.</hi> 1. But yet the <hi>Church</hi> did not ſuffer <hi>alone,</hi> nor was <hi>Religion</hi> the <hi>Onely</hi> bleeding Sacrifice, though the Wounding of <hi>That,</hi> was infinitely <hi>Reproachful</hi> to thoſe who ſold their very <hi>Conſciences,</hi> pretending a Deſign to <hi>Redeem</hi> and <hi>Reſcue</hi> it. The <hi>State</hi> went <hi>Partnerſhip</hi> with the <hi>Church</hi> in its <hi>Loſſes;</hi> and we ſoon ſaw what it was to want a <hi>King,</hi> whoſe <hi>Loins</hi> were not half ſo <hi>heavy</hi> as the <hi>Little Finger</hi> of that <hi>Tyrant</hi> who <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurp'd</hi> His Throne, and was ſuch an <hi>Hardned Reprobate,</hi> as firſt to <hi>Kill,</hi> and then to <hi>take Poſſeſſion. Liberty,</hi> the Darling of the <hi>Nation,</hi> the Bleſſing of <hi>Kings,</hi> but the Engine of <hi>Traytors; Liberty,</hi> that Fools never think <hi>Secure,</hi> till they ſue for it in the <hi>Field,</hi> though they have it in <hi>Poſſeſſion,</hi> and no Man queſtions their <hi>Title: Liberty,</hi> that was uſed to Deſtroy and Purſue <hi>Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> was at laſt <hi>Confined</hi> within the narrow Compaſs of a <hi>Goal</hi> and a <hi>Dungeon.</hi> Nor did it fare better with <hi>Property</hi> neither; for no Man enjoyed ſo much of <hi>That,</hi> as the <hi>Beggar</hi> and the <hi>Bankrupt,</hi> that had little to be robb'd of, but the <hi>Latchet</hi> of his <hi>Shoe. Seque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93420:8"/>
Decimations, Plunders, Forfeitures, Contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Taxes, Loans,</hi> and vaſt Offerings to the <hi>Publick Faith,</hi> ſome or all of theſe devoured all that was ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Inheritance</hi> or <hi>Purchaſe;</hi> and we could call no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing our <hi>Own,</hi> but thoſe <hi>Sins</hi> and <hi>Follies</hi> that had made us Miſerable; at leaſt, no man could promiſe himſelf any <hi>long</hi> Enjoyment of what he had; <hi>Violence</hi> and <hi>Rapine</hi> being all over the Nation the great <hi>Trade</hi> of thoſe Times, ſo that what a Mercenary <hi>Souldier</hi> Left, a Rapacious <hi>Committee-man</hi> would be Sure to Take, unleſs a man would Barter away his <hi>Honour,</hi> and a Bleſſed <hi>Eternity,</hi> by giving up his <hi>Conſcience</hi> as a <hi>Compoſition</hi> and Ranſom for his <hi>Eſtate.</hi> And the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of all this was, becauſe the whole Kingdom was Plunder'd of its <hi>Birth-right;</hi> I mean, the <hi>Law,</hi> which while it was in the Hands of the <hi>King,</hi> was every ones <hi>Security,</hi> from the Peer to the very Meaneſt Subject: and of this the King was ſo Tender to the <hi>laſt,</hi> that juſt before His Martyrdom, when He was offer'd His Life if he would Yield to ſome Conditions which were Inconſiſtent with His <hi>Conſcience</hi> and the <hi>Laws,</hi> He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, That <hi>He would chuſe to die a Thouſand Deaths, before He would Proſtitute His Honour, or Betray the Liberties and Rights of His People.</hi> Every man was <hi>Sure</hi> of his Right, as long as that Religious <hi>Prince</hi> had His juſt <hi>Authority.</hi> But when once <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation</hi> was the Regent, firſt in the <hi>Parliament-Houſe,</hi> and then in the King's <hi>Palace,</hi> we had no <hi>Law</hi> but the <hi>Pleaſure</hi> and <hi>Luſt</hi> of <hi>Tyrants,</hi> whoſe Oppreſſions were <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> becauſe their Power was Arbitrary, and their Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny <hi>Boundleſs.</hi> What was <hi>Magna Charta</hi> worth, when it hung at the Hilt of the <hi>Sword?</hi> And what did you talk of <hi>Laws,</hi> when <hi>Votes</hi> were too <hi>Hard</hi> for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93420:8"/>
               <hi>Statutes?</hi> when Tryals were <hi>Removed</hi> from <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall</hi> to the <hi>Camp?</hi> and <hi>Sentence</hi> was given at the Mouth of the <hi>Cannon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not that this was the Fate onely of the Honeſt <hi>Royaliſt.</hi> Though <hi>His</hi> Miſeries were beyond <hi>meaſure</hi> intolerable, (and he knew not (Poor Wretch!) what to do more, but to ſhed his <hi>Tears,</hi> when his Dread <hi>Soveraign,</hi> the Maſter of his Deareſt Affections, had now ſhed a whole Stream of Blood;) yet the Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the whole <hi>Nation</hi> began now to be Senſible, what a <hi>Miſerable</hi> Bargain was made by the Unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py <hi>Change</hi> of the Times, God ſhewing at once his own <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and Mens <hi>Follies,</hi> by letting them ſee, to their great Coſt, that even Armed <hi>Rebels</hi> rarely get any thing but <hi>Wo,</hi> by a Sad Victory over their Rightful <hi>Soveraign.</hi> The Traitors pretended to fight <hi>for the Safety of the King's Perſon, for the Proteſtant Religion, for the Liberty of the Subject, for the Privileges of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> and <hi>for the Laws and Rights of the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi> In every of theſe reſpects <hi>All</hi> were <hi>Loſers</hi> but the <hi>King:</hi> He indeed got <hi>Two</hi> Crowns for One, a Crown of <hi>Martyrdom,</hi> and a Crown of <hi>Glory,</hi> for a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adem of <hi>Thorns:</hi> But what his <hi>Enemies</hi> gained, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides <hi>Infamy,</hi> and a <hi>Curſe,</hi> and a <hi>ſear'd Conſcience,</hi> with a little <hi>Plunder,</hi> they themſelves will find at the day of <hi>Final</hi> Retribution; and what the <hi>Nation</hi> loſt, we may reckon a little <hi>now.</hi> We loſt a <hi>Prince,</hi> too <hi>Good</hi> for Us to <hi>Keep,</hi> and (Good God!) too <hi>Sacred</hi> to be <hi>Deſtroy'd.</hi> We loſt a <hi>Church,</hi> Beautiful in her <hi>Structure,</hi> Glorious in her <hi>Members,</hi> Militant for her <hi>Head;</hi> and when <hi>that</hi> was ſtruck off, 'twas her <hi>Neceſſary,</hi> but yet <hi>Honourable</hi> Fate, to take her ſhare in the <hi>Martyrdom.</hi> We loſt our <hi>Laws</hi> too; (That indeed was the <hi>firſt</hi> Loſs,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93420:9"/>
when Irreligion Levied that <hi>War</hi> againſt Majeſty, which, in point of Conſcience, and <hi>Law</hi> both, was downright <hi>Rebellion.</hi>) And when our Monarchy, our Religion, our Liberties and Properties were <hi>all</hi> gone, Vengeance went at laſt out of the <hi>Field</hi> to the very Parliament-<hi>houſe,</hi> where all our Miſeries had been <hi>formed,</hi> to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade <hi>Privileges</hi> too, and to let thoſe Butchers of the World ſee, how little even They ſhould get by firſt Beheading the whole <hi>Parliament,</hi> that others might be enabled to Behead the <hi>King</hi> too. The Fall of the two <hi>Hothams,</hi> Father and Son, who were the <hi>firſt</hi> that bad <hi>Open</hi> Deſiance to Majeſty, and gave Him the firſt <hi>Blow;</hi> but in a little time were Executed themſelves<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by the very Maſters that <hi>Employed</hi> them; <hi>their</hi> Fall, I ſay, was an early <hi>Praeſage</hi> of what would afterwards befal the <hi>Reſt,</hi> that were the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> of the King's Ruine. Theſe Two Men denied the King admittance in to <hi>Hull,</hi> though He went thither in <hi>Perſon</hi> to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand it. Soon after, upon Remorſe of Conſcience, they would have <hi>opened</hi> the Gates to Him: but the Parliament now <hi>Hating</hi> their own <hi>Servants</hi> more than they <hi>Feared</hi> their <hi>Soveraign,</hi> Rewarded them at laſt with a Scaffold and an Ax; and by thoſe their own Proceedings, they gave an Unpitied <hi>Example</hi> to <hi>Others</hi> (a Faction that yet ſtood behind the Curtain) to make even <hi>Them</hi> and their <hi>Accomplices</hi> the worſt <hi>Returns,</hi> for their Beſt <hi>Services.</hi> And ſo indeed it fell out, not in the <hi>Country</hi> and <hi>City</hi> onely, but in Both Houſes of <hi>Parliament</hi> alſo. In the Beginning of the Troubles, <hi>Petitioning</hi> was encouraged (under Pretence of being the <hi>Subjects Right</hi>) as a moſt probable Means to bring the King <hi>Low,</hi> and to lay His Honour in the Duſt. But though this <hi>Popular</hi> Method was for ſome time fiercely
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93420:9"/>
cried <hi>up,</hi> as being of dangerous Conſequence to <hi>Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty;</hi> yet when the Faction had ſerved their own <hi>Turn</hi> by it, it was as violently <hi>Oppoſed,</hi> as being of as dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Conſequence to the <hi>Parliament:</hi> So that when the County of <hi>Surry</hi> (in <hi>May,</hi> 1648.) carried a Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Houſe, that tended unto Peace, all of them were <hi>Abuſed,</hi> multitudes of them <hi>Beaten,</hi> many of them <hi>Stripp</hi>'d of their very <hi>Clothes,</hi> and ſeveral of them actually <hi>Killed</hi> upon the Spot. Thus, that which one day was the Subjects <hi>Duty,</hi> another day was their <hi>Sin;</hi> and poor People were taught to uſe <hi>Artifices,</hi> which in the end became their <hi>Snares;</hi> Toyls, to catch the People <hi>themſelves,</hi> after <hi>They</hi> had uſed them to catch their poor <hi>Prince.</hi> This was <hi>one</hi> (but the very <hi>Leaſt</hi>) part of the <hi>Countries</hi> Reward.</p>
            <p>Did it fare better with the <hi>City,</hi> after all its <hi>Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Services, Zeal, Charge, Tumults,</hi> and unparallell'd Wickedneſſes, for a <hi>Damned Cauſe?</hi> We know indeed how it fared, when Vengeance from Heaven ſtruck it <hi>down</hi> into the <hi>Duſt,</hi> to Expiate (if it were poſſible) its Sins by <hi>Fire.</hi> But how, I pray, did Matters go here about the <hi>Period</hi> and <hi>Cloſe</hi> of the <hi>War?</hi> Do not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny now alive Remember, how <hi>Miſerably</hi> (I cannot ſay, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſtly</hi>) this City was uſed in 1647; how it was Over-awed and Haraſſed even by thoſe very Men, whoſe Hands the City had <hi>Arm'd</hi> and <hi>Strengthned</hi> againſt its <hi>Prince?</hi> Upon the Apprentices Inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, did not <hi>Cromwell</hi> Threaten (nay, Command his Forces) <hi>to Kill Man, Woman, and Child, and to Fire the City?</hi> Were not Speeches made in the Commons Houſe to Confiſcate the Eſtates of many the moſt Eminent and Wealthy <hi>Citizens,</hi> and to take off their <hi>Heads?</hi> Were not the Aldermen and others commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93420:10"/>
to the <hi>Gaol,</hi> the Poſts and Chains pulled up, and the whole City left to viſible Dangers of a <hi>Maſſacre?</hi> Was not the Tower ſeiz'd, the Fortifications about the Town demoliſhed, the Militia voted out of the City<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hands, and every Houſe expoſed to the Mercies of an Outragious Enemy, that was clothed with <hi>Plunder,</hi> and fed with <hi>Blood?</hi> Did not an <hi>Inſolent General</hi> ride with his Army through the Streets, for no other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but to Treat <hi>Fools</hi> at laſt with <hi>Scorn, Contumely,</hi> and <hi>Reproach,</hi> and to <hi>Triumph</hi> over thoſe who had <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted</hi> ſo effectually to <hi>Beat</hi> and <hi>Conquer</hi> their <hi>King?</hi> Theſe, and I know not how many ſuch like Uſages more, were the <hi>Cities</hi> Reward; not to ſpeak of a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> (and then in a manner the <hi>Onely</hi>) Trade that was here driven, of <hi>Impoſitions</hi> and <hi>Loans,</hi> and a Thouſand Prefidious <hi>Tricks,</hi> to Cheat men at laſt of thoſe vaſt Sums wherewith Zeal and Impiety had liberally en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted the <hi>Publick Faith:</hi> All which <hi>Diſgraceful</hi> and <hi>Contumelious</hi> Treatments, Men, though they might be then very <hi>ſenſible</hi> of their paſt <hi>Follies,</hi> were <hi>Forced</hi> to yield and ſubmit to <hi>Tamely,</hi> a Powerful and Vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rane Army lying near the Town, to keep People in <hi>awe,</hi> and to hold them by the <hi>Throats,</hi> while their Friends at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> pick'd their <hi>Purſes,</hi> and carried away their <hi>Money. Theſe were thy Gods, O Iſrael;</hi> Theſe were <hi>London</hi>'s <hi>Patriots, London</hi>'s <hi>Tutelar Saints,</hi> the <hi>Deities</hi> and <hi>Idols</hi> that <hi>London Worſhipp'd</hi> and <hi>Bowed</hi> down to, when ſhe <hi>Forſwore</hi> her <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and Raiſed ſuch Formidable <hi>Mutinies,</hi> firſt againſt the Earl of <hi>Straf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and then againſt the <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe were <hi>Strange</hi> Returns (one would think) for a <hi>Confiding</hi> City to Receive, after all her <hi>Perjuries,</hi> after all thoſe Forces of Men and Money which ſhe had
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93420:10"/>
Employed to bring her diſtreſſed Prince to the Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, (for that was the <hi>Event</hi> and Natural <hi>Conſequence,</hi> whatever the <hi>Intentions</hi> of ſome were, who did not look ſo far at the <hi>Firſt.</hi>) But if we go on now, and enquire <hi>further</hi> into the Story, we ſhall find, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> themſelves that <hi>Blew</hi> the <hi>Trumpet,</hi> and Sent out the <hi>Drum,</hi> gained nothing <hi>neither,</hi> but had reaſon to <hi>weep</hi> too, and Infinitely <hi>more</hi> than others, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that their utmoſt <hi>Acqueſt</hi> was <hi>Guilt</hi> and <hi>Reproach,</hi> and a Perpetual <hi>Curſe</hi> upon their Names For even <hi>They</hi> were paid in their own Coin, and were ſerved Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as they had ſerved the Government, having ſoon Loſt that which they called the King's <hi>Politick Capacity,</hi> when they had Ruin'd His <hi>Perſon.</hi> When Cornet <hi>Joyce</hi> had <hi>Surpriſed</hi> His Majeſty at <hi>Holmeby,</hi> bragging of his Exploit, he told <hi>Cromwell,</hi> That now he had the King in <hi>his Power: Well,</hi> (ſaid <hi>Cromwell</hi>) and then I doubt not but <hi>I ſhall have the Parliament in my Pocket.</hi> And the truth is, He never had <hi>Money</hi> ſo much at his <hi>Command,</hi> as now he had thoſe who had hitherto been his <hi>Maſters,</hi> and kept him in Pay. Such was his Diabolical <hi>Craft,</hi> his Monſtrous and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlative <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> and his Inſeparable <hi>Intereſt</hi> with a Potent Faction, that were linked with him in the Communion of the Higheſt <hi>Crimes,</hi> that the Traitors which were of a <hi>Meaner</hi> Size, were Manag'd at his <hi>Pleaſure;</hi> and 'tis obſervable, that by the <hi>ſame</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods and Artifices he Bafled and Outed <hi>Them,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>They</hi> had Leſſened and Deſtroyed their <hi>Soveraign.</hi> The Parliament was now divided into <hi>Presbyterian</hi> and <hi>Independent:</hi> and <hi>each</hi> Houſe <hi>ſtrove</hi> againſt the <hi>other;</hi> yet <hi>Both</hi> claſhed within <hi>Themſelves,</hi> till the <hi>Army-Officers,</hi> grown now too <hi>Hard</hi> for their <hi>Maſters,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:93420:11"/>
turned their <hi>own</hi> Arts upon them, and got a Victory over <hi>them</hi> All, as they had over their Calamitous, but Anointed Lord. Thoſe Lords that Conſented to the Excluſion of the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> to the taking away of the King's <hi>Negative Voice,</hi> and to the Vote againſt <hi>all fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Addreſſes</hi> to His Majeſty, were in a ſhort ſpace deprived of their <hi>own</hi> Negative Votes, were <hi>Deſpiſed</hi> in all Proceedings, (the Commons acting as they pleas'd <hi>without</hi> them) and in the End were turn'd out of Doors, leaving nothing behind them in the Houſe, but the Memory of having Violated their Honour there, by being Unfortunate Inſtruments of Undoing Him, who was the Nobility's <hi>Defence</hi> againſt the Rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of the <hi>Rabble.</hi> The <hi>Commons</hi> could not agree in <hi>Peace,</hi> though they had Confederated in the Guilt of an Unjuſt <hi>War;</hi> but fell <hi>Foul</hi> upon one <hi>another,</hi> as they had done upon their <hi>Prince;</hi> till they were by many <hi>Purgations</hi> Weakned, by many <hi>Reſtraints</hi> Bafled, by many <hi>Menaces</hi> Overawed, and by many Armed Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-<hi>Traytors</hi> firſt <hi>Vanquiſh'd,</hi> and then <hi>Expelled:</hi> So that <hi>their</hi> Reward too was onely a <hi>Miſerable Life,</hi> to ſee <hi>Privileges</hi> deſtroyed after <hi>Prerogative,</hi> and the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Nation Shifted, out of the Hands of a <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch,</hi> into the Claws of a <hi>Monſter,</hi> whoſe Early <hi>Vices</hi> had made him a <hi>Beggar,</hi> whoſe Contempt of <hi>God</hi> had made him an <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> whoſe <hi>Ambition</hi> had encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him to be an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper,</hi> and whoſe <hi>Sanguinary Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> made him a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> a <hi>Parricide,</hi> and the <hi>Plague</hi> of <hi>Mankind,</hi> till God in his Mercy to us put an Unexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Period to his Life, and the Devil, whom he had long ſerved, carried him away to his Proper Place.</p>
            <p>It is not to be wondred at, that an Hoſt of Cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trices ſhould thus pick out the Eyes of thoſe our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praeſentatives,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93420:11"/>
and render their Houſe Deſolate and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſpitable: for That was the Cockatrices <hi>Neſt;</hi> and when They had warmed the <hi>Eggs,</hi> and <hi>Hatched</hi> the Creatures, there was reaſon enough to Fear, that being once grown up, they would infeſt not the <hi>Nation</hi> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but <hi>Them</hi> too; becauſe Rebellion and Treaſon ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom laſt long; and, ſuch is the Juſtice of God, that Villanies, though <hi>Proſperous</hi> for a <hi>Time,</hi> turn at laſt to a Sad Account, both to the <hi>Projectors</hi> and <hi>Inſtruments</hi> of them; and ſo we found the Courſe of things to go, as well in the <hi>Management,</hi> as at the <hi>End</hi> of that Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy War. For, not the <hi>Parliament</hi> onely, but their <hi>Forces</hi> and <hi>Stipendiaries</hi> Suffer'd too; the Juſt God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creeing to Plague the very <hi>Miniſters</hi> and <hi>Executioners</hi> of Treaſon, though he was pleaſ'd to Behold their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolencies <hi>a while,</hi> and then took away his Anointed, to let Mad-men ſee, how Happy they <hi>might</hi> have been, had they not been their <hi>Own</hi> Enemies, as well as <hi>His.</hi> The Armed <hi>Independent</hi> ſoon tripp'd up the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi>'s Heels: though the One marched out in the <hi>Front,</hi> and did cut out the <hi>Way,</hi> yet the Other fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in the <hi>Rear,</hi> and firſt Caſhier'd <hi>him,</hi> and then went away with the <hi>Spoil.</hi> The Reformation of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> began the Quarrel, and the Diſciplinarian fought with Zeal for a Wretched Covenant, for which he had pawned his Conſcience and Soul, as well as Plighted his Troth. But the <hi>Other</hi> Sectaries aimed at the total Subverſion of the <hi>Government</hi> in Church and State too; and to compaſs this End the better, they Diſarm'd the Hands of him, whom they knew to be an Hairy, but Perſidious Brother: and ſo, you know, the whole Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia was Purged over and over, the Army was new-Officer'd, Confinding Brethren were put in the room of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93420:12"/>
thoſe Puny Saints, that were afraid to go above <hi>half</hi> way on the Errand, and Proteſted they would <hi>Preſerve</hi> the King and His Dignities, though they Deſtroyed the Eſtabliſhments of the Church. Therefore when the <hi>Covenanter</hi> had been ſufficiently uſed as a <hi>Toel</hi> and <hi>Property</hi> to do a conſiderable <hi>Part</hi> of the great Work of Darkneſs, then <hi>Others</hi> thought it time for Them to ſlep in, to go <hi>through</hi> with it; and ſo the Silly Kirk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were for the moſt part Laugh'd at and Diſcarded, and cheated of their Ends, and their Dear Convenant was Cried down, as <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> had been before, the moſt Powerful Faction having now Supplanted the <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> as the Presbyterian had Supplanted the Honeſt <hi>Cavalier;</hi> by which means the Power of the Sword fell into the Hands of a Juncto, that hitherto had not been Diſcovered, nor perhaps Suſpected; and then in ſtead of a Full Parliament by <hi>Weſtminſter-hall,</hi> you had a Committee of Grandees at <hi>Derby-houſe,</hi> that Voted, Manag'd, Deſtroyed, and Ruin'd all; neither Sparing, nor Reverencing the very Crowned Head. Nay, to add <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Diſgrace</hi> to our Miſeries, this Faction was molded and made up of thoſe who were Notorious for Debauch'd Principles, for Atheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Spirits, for Proffigate Lives, for Impure Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ees, for Savage Minds, and moſtly too for ſuch a <hi>Baſe</hi> and <hi>Abject</hi> Condition, that they were not onely the <hi>Plague,</hi> but the very <hi>Vermine</hi> of the Nation; a Pack of Fornicators, Bankrupts, Blaſphemers of the Holy Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Beggars, and Mechanicks of all ſorts, Labourers at <hi>Furnaces</hi> and <hi>Stalls,</hi> and the like; theſe were the Honourable, the Right Honourable, His Excellence, His Highneſs, and ſuch Filth of Falſe Heraldry, that they were a Reproach and Blemiſh to <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93420:12"/>
               <hi>Honeſty,</hi> to the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> ſhall I ſay? nay, a Diſhonour to the <hi>Hangman,</hi> a Stain and Diſgrace to the very <hi>Gallows.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet had not theſe very <hi>Regicides</hi> neither more Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to <hi>Inſalt</hi> over the Miſeries of <hi>Others,</hi> than to <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> their <hi>Own.</hi> For want of that <hi>vigorous</hi> Life and Soul, which is Infuſed into all Juſt Authority that hath <hi>Law</hi> for its Parent, <hi>their</hi> Power was in a manner Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled in the <hi>Birth:</hi> and they themſelves that <hi>Survived</hi> it a little, were ſoon made Signal Inſtances of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Juſtice, which upon a Miraculous <hi>Revolution</hi> juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly overtook them; ſo that an Hateful and Unpitied <hi>Death</hi> was all the Advantage they gained at the Cloſe of their Unparallell'd Villanies. And as for their <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity</hi> and <hi>Families</hi> they leſt behind them, ſuch as have made curious Enquiries into the thing, have Obſerved, That they bear to this day the Characters and Marks of Divine Vengeance, and have little but a Curſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailed upon them for their Inheritance; as if the Hand of God had Stigmatiz'd <hi>Them,</hi> as he did <hi>Cain;</hi> and Curſed them with ſuch a Portion as he left the <hi>Jews,</hi> for Cruciſying our Saviour.</p>
            <p>Thus I have in ſome meaſure repreſented the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal</hi> Miſeries which attended our Late Captivity both in Church and State, nay in the very <hi>Camp</hi> too: and I have the Longer and the more Particularly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted upon this Theme, for the Information of thoſe, who through their <hi>Ignorance</hi> of the Condition of thoſe Times, are in danger of being miſ-led into Practices which naturally tend to draw on a <hi>Second</hi> Captivity. For Treaſon did not die with thoſe Regicides; neither was the Art of King-killing the Sin of <hi>this</hi> Day <hi>onely.</hi> The Drinking of Blood once, leaves (it ſeems) an
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93420:13"/>
Appetite and <hi>Thirſt</hi> after More, in ſtead of Troubling Rebels Bowels, and working a True Repentance for that which hath been ſhed <hi>already.</hi> Though His Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Majeſty hath been ready to Forgive many wicked Men their <hi>Treaſons,</hi> yet we do not find that They have been as ready to Forgive Him His <hi>Mercies:</hi> no; that they might be <hi>Revenged</hi> rather upon Him for His <hi>Act of Oblivion</hi> to many that were Acceſſories to His <hi>Father's</hi> Blood, they have Studied and Plotted how to embrue their Hands in <hi>His</hi> Blood too: the thing is ſo Plain, by ſo many Unqueſtionable and Concurring Proofs, and even by the Joint Confeſſion of Criminals, that whoſoever ſhall go about to Deny or Mince the Late (I wiſh I could not ſay, the Preſent) Conſpiracy, ought not (I think) to be look'd upon as a <hi>By-ſtander,</hi> but an <hi>Accomplice</hi> and <hi>Confederate</hi> in the Treaſon. The Truth is, theſe Demonſtrative Evidences have abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly Satisfied the <hi>Law:</hi> but there were Arguments enough <hi>before,</hi> to confirm the <hi>Opinion</hi> of <hi>every</hi> Sagaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and <hi>Honeſt</hi> Man, that a total Deſtruction of Prince and Government was intended, and carrying on <hi>again.</hi> For, what, I pray, was the late <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> but a <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript</hi> of the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant?</hi> onely the Copy <hi>exceeded,</hi> and was <hi>worſe</hi> than the Original; and yet <hi>That</hi> did coſt the whole Kingdom its <hi>Peace,</hi> and the King his <hi>Head.</hi> Thoſe numerous <hi>Riots</hi> and terrible <hi>Confluences</hi> of Diſaffected and Factious Men, which were ſeen a while ago, what was it but a <hi>Numbring</hi> of the People, a Caſting up of their Strength and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, till the Demagogues ſhould think it fit to Adjourn from the <hi>City</hi> into the <hi>Field?</hi> The <hi>Forcing</hi> of that <hi>Petitioning-Trade,</hi> which of late was ſo General over the whole Nation, what was it Deſigned for by Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93420:13"/>
Huckſters of Miſchief, but to render the King and His Government a <hi>Grievance,</hi> and to Diſpoſe Men for <hi>another</hi> Rebellion? that is, to Sell the Nations <hi>Peace,</hi> and to Purchaſe a <hi>Crown.</hi> Thoſe Baſe <hi>Reflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> which have been (nay, which are ſtill) publickly made upon His Majeſty, and His Miniſters of State, what is the meaning of them, but to make Him <hi>Odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> and to Deſtroy Him <hi>Effectually,</hi> by Murdering Him firſt in the <hi>Affections</hi> of His Subjects; it being Impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for the moſt Active and Malicious Villains to ſtrike Him with an <hi>Ax,</hi> till they have ſlain His <hi>Credit,</hi> and laid His <hi>Honour</hi> in the Duſt? The Reprinting of <hi>Doleman,</hi> and the Diſperſing of a Thouſand Other Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, full of Seditious and Jeſuitical Principles, is the very <hi>ſame</hi> thing that was Practiſed in the <hi>Former</hi> Times; and there could be no other Reaſon for it, but to Juſtifie <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Regicide</hi> again; it being Unconceivable why the very ſame <hi>Methods</hi> ſhould be uſed <hi>again,</hi> unleſs the ſame <hi>Deſigns</hi> were at the <hi>End</hi> of all. Thoſe Popular but Abſurd <hi>Fears,</hi> that all our Throats would be Cut in a Night, is a <hi>Stale</hi> and <hi>Known</hi> Inſtrument of Rebellion: for a great Noiſe of ſuch Dangers was thrown about in the beginning of the <hi>Late</hi> Troubles, ſo that it was Reported, and Credited too, That the very <hi>Thames</hi> was to be blown up with Gunpowder, to Stifle every one with Water in their Beds. The Inordinate Apprehenſion of the Dangers of Arbitrary Power, every man knows that 'twas an <hi>Old</hi> Device that ſerved to bring it in. There are Twenty things more I might take notice of, were it needful, to ſhew how Induſtrious Some pretending Patriots and Reformers have been to act over <hi>again</hi> thoſe Seven years Sins, which cauſed that Havock,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93420:14"/>
and Bloodſhed, and Ruine both of Prince and People, from 41, to 48. All the Kings Miſeries, and our own Calamities, were brought about by Confederacies, by Tumults, by Mutinous Complaints of Grievances, by Seditious Pamphlets, by Defamations of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by years of Tyranny, by all manner of Jeſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Practices, by Inſolent and Impious Votes, by bringing the King into Straits, by anſwering His Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities with Remonſtrances in ſtead of Supplies, by crying out againſt Evil Counſellors, by pulling and tugging at Favourites, by declaiming againſt Biſhops and Ceremonies, by Schiſmatical Aſſemblies, and by a great many Stratagems more, which have been late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet on work again ſo viſibly and plainly, that we had reaſon enough to <hi>ſuſpect</hi> the Blackeſt Deſigns, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ever we heard of or <hi>Miſtruſted</hi> the Villany intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the <hi>Rye-houſe.</hi> For theſe Several years laſt paſt, I think there hath been nothing <hi>New,</hi> but <hi>Ignoramus Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> and a gainful Trade of <hi>Swearing</hi> and <hi>Ferſwearing</hi> at the <hi>Bar:</hi> all the <hi>other</hi> Practices were a Repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Old, Tried</hi> Artifices, which ſome Experienced <hi>Achitophels</hi> made uſe of again, becauſe they had <hi>once</hi> a <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>atum eſt,</hi> and became <hi>Succeſsful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O for the Love of God let us learn to be Wiſe, and to beware in <hi>Time,</hi> and not venture the Sad Reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of a <hi>Late</hi> Repentance; eſpecially ſince God has been ſo Merciful unto us, that, in ſpite of all the Stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings of our Enemies, he hath Kept us Safe, even when we were in the <hi>Dark,</hi> and hath now laid open the Dangers we were in to every mans <hi>view.</hi> This was the Aggravation of the Folly and Miſery of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that ſhe Conſidered not well of things till ſhe was quite a Captive. She remembred in the days of her
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93420:14"/>
               <hi>Affliction,</hi> and of her <hi>Miſeries,</hi> all her <hi>pleaſant things that ſhe had in the days of old,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Lam. 1. 7. By the Rivers of</hi> Babylon, <hi>there the</hi> Jews <hi>ſat down, and wept:</hi> but then it was too <hi>late;</hi> they ſhould have bethought themſelves <hi>Before,</hi> while it was yet in their power to have <hi>Prevented</hi> their Captivity. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not imagine what is likely to work upon People, if nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Other</hi> mens Experience, nor their <hi>Own,</hi> will teach them to beware. Yet this is one thing that maketh the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ridiculous <hi>Abroad,</hi> and Unfortunate at <hi>Home,</hi> that generally they are apt to <hi>Try Concluſions,</hi> and to make <hi>Freſh</hi> Experiments ſtill, though they have ſmart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſeverely for their Silly Attempts, and have ſo often tried things to <hi>Evil</hi> and <hi>Miſerable</hi> Purpoſes. One would think, our Condition and Caſe the other day was ſuch, that we ſhould not <hi>Forget</hi> it, much leſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to make it our <hi>Option</hi> and Lot once <hi>more.</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks it ſhould be ſufficient Warning to us, not to flatter our ſelves with Fancies, and Probabilities, and Praeſumptions of our <hi>own,</hi> becauſe we have found, to our great Coſt, that in all <hi>Conſiderable,</hi> eſpecially <hi>Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent</hi> Alterations, there is nothing <hi>Certain,</hi> but <hi>Miſery.</hi> For, as it is Impoſſible for this Kingdom to be Happy, but upon thoſe Foundations whereon it Stands <hi>now</hi> both in <hi>Sacred</hi> and <hi>Civil</hi> Matters; ſo it is impoſſible for men to <hi>Tear</hi> up thoſe Foundations, but they muſt fall themſelves under the <hi>Ruines</hi> of the Building. Nor is it enough to ſay, Thus far onely we intend to go, we would take away this Rafter, and remove that Beam, that is ſuch an Eye-ſore unto us; but will not meddle with, or diſturb the <hi>Ground-work:</hi> for when men begin to Mend a whole Kingdom, by taking it into pieces, God alone Knoweth how far Some may
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93420:15"/>
be <hi>Tempted,</hi> others may be <hi>Conſtrained</hi> to proceed at laſt. Read but the Hiſtory of the <hi>Late</hi> Times, and you will find how far the Event ran out beyond the firſt Intentions, nay, beyond the Expectations and Suſpicions of Many, who were very Active and Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in Beginning the War againſt His Majeſty. But having once drawn the Sword, they thought it Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adviſable to Sheath it again; becauſe, being Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of their Guilt, they were <hi>Afraid</hi> of Juſtice which they had Deſerved, and <hi>Doubtful</hi> of Mercy which was Precarious; and therefore never thought themſelves Safe, but by <hi>Accumulating</hi> Crimes to a great Bulk; and ſo one Miſchief brought on another, till all ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated in the Deſtruction of the King, which was the <hi>Capital</hi> Miſchief. 'Tis likely this was not the <hi>Primary</hi> Deſign; nay, perhaps it was not Deſigned at all by many of them, (though it be hard to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that they did not intend the <hi>End,</hi> who uſed the <hi>Means.</hi>) But whatever <hi>Their</hi> meaning might be, <hi>Others</hi> that ſtood Undiſcern'd in a Dark Corner of the Houſe, made an <hi>Improvement</hi> of that Treaſon which the reſt had <hi>Begun,</hi> ſo that it was out of the Power of the Honeſter ſort to Save the Life of that Prince, whoſe Honour and Intereſt they had Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd. For the <hi>Power</hi> ſhifted with the <hi>Sword,</hi> out of one Hand into another, as every one could catch it. The Parliament Snatch'd it from the <hi>King,</hi> and put it into the Hands of an <hi>Army:</hi> the Army was <hi>Divided,</hi> and though the Presbyterians managed it <hi>Firſt,</hi> yet the Independents ſoon wreſted it out of <hi>their</hi> Clutches, and held it till it fell to the Share of a Fanatick <hi>Committee,</hi> that were Reſolved to Embrue it in the King's <hi>Blood;</hi> which the <hi>Firſt</hi> Actors could
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93420:15"/>
no more hinder then, than they could command a Tempeſt, or govern an Inundation with their <hi>Breath:</hi> And by theſe Means All of them were <hi>more</hi> or <hi>leſs</hi> guilty of Murdering His Majeſty; becauſe One Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction <hi>Hunted</hi> Him till they drove Him to the <hi>Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold,</hi> and the Other preſently provided a <hi>Block</hi> and <hi>Ax</hi> for Him, and ſo <hi>Both</hi> were Murderers; becauſe 'tis the ſame thing in effect, whether a Man be Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the Slow Methods of a <hi>War,</hi> or by a <hi>Haſty</hi> Blow, and a <hi>Speedy</hi> Stab.</p>
            <p>Now this ſhould be enough to <hi>Warn</hi> and <hi>Terrifie</hi> every well-meaning Perſon among Us, from having any the leaſt <hi>Fellowſhip</hi> with, nay from lending ſo much as an <hi>Ear</hi> to thoſe Malecontents of Our days, who are given to Change, and onely wait for an <hi>Opportunity.</hi> For it is Impoſſible to be Innocent long in the midſt of Such Temptations; becauſe a little <hi>Communion</hi> in Evil, and the very <hi>Courſe</hi> of things, will of Neceſſity <hi>drive</hi> all Unwary Men ſo far by <hi>degrees,</hi> as to bring them under the Guilt of the <hi>Higheſt</hi> Crimes at <hi>laſt,</hi> though as <hi>yet</hi> they be not Diſaffected to the Government. One ſaith, I am for our <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy;</hi> another, I am for <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> too; a Third, I am for the whole Frame of the Government as it is now <hi>Eſtabliſh'd by Law;</hi> and <hi>All</hi> theſe ſay, God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid that we ſhould have any hand in <hi>Killing</hi> or <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing</hi> the King, or in ſetting up another <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth:</hi> No, we would onely Keep out <hi>Popery,</hi> and ſecure our ſelves againſt <hi>Arbitrary Power;</hi> and then we will give <hi>over.</hi> Now all this is Juſtifiable and Good, as long as the Means are <hi>Honeſt,</hi> and Men are <hi>Sincere.</hi> But then, Conſider, I pray, what thoſe <hi>Methods</hi> be which are <hi>Propoſed</hi> by Popular <hi>Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:93420:16"/>
for the Accompliſhing of theſe Ends. Are they not the very Methods of the <hi>Old</hi> Conſpiracy, Revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and Set out in a <hi>New Edition,</hi> and with <hi>Augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations</hi> too? Is not another <hi>Rebellion</hi> formed? Do not the Ring-leaders (moſt of whom have no Religion at all) go to work again by Spreading of Lies and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies, by raiſing many groundleſs Jealouſies, by increaſing Fears beyond a due meaſure, by Conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Trucking with all ſorts of Sects and Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, by Uſurping a Power over Crowns, and by ſuch manifeſt Endeavours to ſpoil the King of His Rega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, that had not the wonderful Providence of God interpos'd, they had long ago made a Spoil of His very Life too? Theſe Practices are Open and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, and as Viſible as the Sun: and we ought with all manner of Diligence and Shyneſs to <hi>Beware</hi> of Men that deal in Arts of this <hi>Horrid</hi> Nature, leſt we be led like Fools into Captivity <hi>again,</hi> and be forced to Loſe not our <hi>Tears</hi> onely, but our <hi>Blood</hi> too, when 'twill be too <hi>Late</hi> to ſay, We did not think that Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters would have come to this Miſerable paſs. When Men think to go ſo far, but no <hi>farther,</hi> they ſhould conſider how much farther <hi>Others</hi> may go by their <hi>Example</hi> and <hi>Encouragement;</hi> they ſhould have a Care that they lend them not neither an Helping <hi>Hand,</hi> nor ſo much as a <hi>Finger;</hi> for fear that the <hi>Leaſt</hi> Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance may be Fatal. In the <hi>Former</hi> Times, though ſome did from the <hi>Beginning</hi> deſign (as many of Late have done) the killing of their Prince; and though endeavours were uſed by a Baſe Faction, firſt in the Northern Camp, then at <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> and at laſt in the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Wight,</hi> to make him away <hi>Privately,</hi> either by <hi>Piſtol,</hi> or <hi>Poiſon,</hi> or ſome other means of Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſſination,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93420:16"/>
yet the <hi>generality</hi> of People did not dream of it, much leſs did they believe that any could be ſo Diabolically Impudent and Wicked, as to Murder him <hi>Publickly</hi> under Colour of <hi>Juſtice:</hi> but yet Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd he <hi>was</hi> after that manner; and our Nation ſince hath lain under ſuch Guilt by it, as God alone know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth when it will be <hi>Expiated.</hi> I am ſure, the ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>more</hi> Blood is not the way to <hi>Atone</hi> for the ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of that; but a ready way rather to provoke a Juſt God to cut us down Root and Branch, that we be no more a People. Every the leaſt drop of our <hi>Princes</hi> Blood is Sacred, and more to be valued by us than the Blood of our <hi>Parents;</hi> and that none of that Blood may hereafter be upon <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> or upon our <hi>Children,</hi> for God's ſake let us be very careful of theſe two things; and ſo we will Conclude.</p>
            <p>1. That we ſtifle all <hi>Conceptions</hi> of Diſloyalty in our very <hi>Thoughts,</hi> that we choke even the <hi>Beginnings</hi> of it, and that we abſtain not onely from all <hi>Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> of Wickedneſs of this kind, but from all <hi>Poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities</hi> of Guilt. <hi>He that hateth his Brother is a Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer;</hi> and ſo he that entertaineth any Undutiful and Unworthy Apprehenſions of his Prince, is in a ready way to be a Regicide. Out of the Heart proceed evil Surmiſes, Jealouſies, Fears, Hatreds; thence Men go on to Blaſphemies, and Reproaches of a Princes Actions, and Government, and the baſeſt Miſconſtructions that can be made of his Counſels and Adminiſtrations, though they be for the moſt part Honourable, and in all points Innocent and Juſt: And when the <hi>Heart,</hi> and the <hi>Tongue</hi> both are ſet on Fire, the whole <hi>Kingdom</hi> will be preſently ſet on Fire <hi>too;</hi> and 'tis twenty to one but the King <hi>himſelf</hi> is made at laſt a Flaming <hi>Sacrifice.</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:93420:17"/>
Theſe were the <hi>Original</hi> ſins in the <hi>late</hi> times: From Idle <hi>Jealouſies,</hi> which Undutiful Spirits were very Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptive of, they went to Hard <hi>Words,</hi> from Words to <hi>Blows,</hi> and at laſt the War ended in the Barbarous <hi>Parricide</hi> that was acted upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Great Father of our Countrey; though to ſtill (if it were poſſible) the Madneſs of the People, he was willing to part with <hi>any</hi> thing, but his <hi>whole Crown</hi> and his <hi>Conſcience.</hi> And yet, to ſee what a ſad Fate commonly attends an <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient</hi> and <hi>Heady</hi> Generation, when his dangers of being deſtroy'd were now <hi>Open</hi> and <hi>Manifeſt,</hi> all conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Perſons that had any regard for Humanity and Religion, were preſently in a <hi>Rage.</hi> And, not onely many <hi>Honourable</hi> Perſons, who had <hi>ever</hi> been <hi>Faithful</hi> and <hi>True</hi> to Him, and particularly thoſe truly <hi>Loyal</hi> and <hi>Noble</hi> Lords, <hi>Hertford, Richmond, Southampton, Lindſey,</hi> and ſome more, freely offered themſelves to <hi>Die,</hi> and be <hi>Sacrificed</hi> for him; but alſo very many of thoſe who had been the Unfortunate <hi>Inſtruments</hi> of his Ruine, <hi>Relented</hi> when they ſaw the Ax <hi>coming,</hi> and would have <hi>hindred</hi> the intended Barbarity, being brought at laſt to a Senſe, whether of their <hi>Sin,</hi> or of their <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery,</hi> I cannot tell. The <hi>Scots</hi> Proteſted againſt it; but, alas! it was too <hi>Late;</hi> and their ſtrength was now gone, <hi>before</hi> their Prince, the <hi>Glory</hi> of their Nation fell. Conſiderable <hi>Inſurrections</hi> were in ſeveral parts of this Kingdom for the Liberty of their Soveraign. The <hi>London Apprentices</hi> took Arms, to <hi>Atone</hi> (if they could) for their <hi>Maſters</hi> Crimes, and to <hi>Deliver</hi> their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <hi>Prince.</hi> The <hi>Parliament,</hi> that now ſaw the ſad <hi>iſſues</hi> of their Diſobedience, voted an <hi>Agreement</hi> with His Majeſty. Onely from the <hi>Army,</hi> and the Veteran Faction of the <hi>City,</hi> Petitions came for <hi>Juſtice</hi> againſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93420:17"/>
Him. All <hi>other</hi> Faces gathered <hi>Blackneſs</hi> through Horror and Amazement at the intended Villany; nay, many of thoſe very <hi>Miniſters,</hi> who had thrown Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands from the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> would now have <hi>Quenched</hi> them with their <hi>Tears;</hi> they <hi>Repented,</hi> as <hi>Judas</hi> did; but were at laſt <hi>Deſpiſed</hi> and <hi>Hated</hi> by the Faction that had hitherto <hi>Abetted</hi> them, but now could have been well pleaſed, if, as they <hi>Repented,</hi> ſo they would have <hi>Hanged</hi> themſelves too, as <hi>Judas</hi> (their Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brother) did, after he had <hi>Betrayed the Innocent Blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is enough to ſhew, what a <hi>Dangerous</hi> Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is for People but to <hi>Affect</hi> Innovation, and to be <hi>Diſpos'd</hi> for it; and how Neceſſary it is for Us, that would live Quietly in the Land, to Stifle all manner of <hi>Diſloyalty</hi> in the very <hi>Beginnings,</hi> leſt by giving <hi>way</hi> to thoſe things which already have Cauſed the Subverſion of our Government and Laws, and the Death of the King, we ſhould fall again into <hi>Diſtractions</hi> and <hi>Outrages,</hi> till by the Wiles and Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Evil Men, we be led like Fools to the Correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Stocks, and make our ſelves Captives once <hi>more,</hi> beyond all Hopes or Poſſibilities of Redemption.</p>
            <p>2. And in order thereunto, let us all be very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, in the <hi>next</hi> place, to keep our <hi>Brains</hi> from being Infected with thoſe <hi>Vicious</hi> Principles, which the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of our Peace are wont to uſe as <hi>Tools</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments</hi> to bring all their Bloody and Execrable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies to <hi>Effect:</hi> I mean, ſuch Principles as Theſe; That <hi>the King's Power is not derived immediately from God, but from the People;</hi> That <hi>by their own Voluntary Act the People do make Princes their Commiſſioners and Truſtees;</hi> That <hi>they may call Him to account, if they judge him to have failed in the Execution of His Office;</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:93420:18"/>
That <hi>if He will not come to Trial with Tameneſs and Submiſſion, the People may uſe any Force or Violence againſt Him;</hi> That <hi>upon Proof and Conviction touching His Breach of Truſt, they may Condemn, Depoſe, and Kill Him if they pleaſe, and Diſpoſe of the Crown according as they ſhall think beſt for the Peoples Good.</hi> They that thus make <hi>Court</hi> to the <hi>People,</hi> as if all Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty were in <hi>Them,</hi> and would make them believe that They have <hi>Really</hi> that Power which the <hi>Devil</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to, of <hi>Beſtowing Kingdoms,</hi> can deſign nothing elſe but to <hi>Debauch</hi> Men out of their <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and to fit them for the perpetrating of any the moſt <hi>Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid</hi> Villanies: and whoſoever he be that is ſtrongly perſuaded of the <hi>Truth</hi> of thoſe <hi>Principles,</hi> wants no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>Opportunity</hi> and an <hi>Ax</hi> to make him a <hi>Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide.</hi> The Faction of the Late Times, to Juſtifie (if they could) their Proceedings againſt the King, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed a Treaſonable Book, which had been written by a moſt violent <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> under the Counterfeit Name of <hi>Doleman,</hi> with ſome few Alterations to Diſguiſe it; which very Libel was Lately Printed again entire by the Faction <hi>now,</hi> though it was Condemned by Act of Parliament in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> Now<note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt. of Indep. <hi>p. 113.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>Fundamental</hi> Principle in that Book is this, That <hi>every Commonwealth hath Power within it ſelf to Diſpoſe of the Governours, and either to Alter or Aboliſh any Form of Government, according to the Pleaſure of the People.</hi> A little before the King's <hi>Tryal,</hi> the Peſtilent <hi>Remnant</hi> of the Houſe of Commons, that were now at the Armies <hi>Devotion,</hi> to <hi>Prepare</hi> the Kings way firſt to the <hi>Court,</hi> and ſo to the <hi>Scaffold,</hi> agreed upon this Vote, (as if they had been a Conclave of Jeſuites) That <hi>the People under God are the Original of all Juſt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:93420:18"/>
Power.</hi> And upon this Fundamental Principle they raiſed theſe other Poſitions, which were the Natural Conſequents of it; 1. <hi>That the Commons of</hi> England <hi>Aſſembled in Parliament, have the Supreme Authority of the Nation.</hi> 2. That <hi>whatſoever is declared for Law by the Commons, hath the force of a Law.</hi> 3. That <hi>all the People of the Nation are concluded thereby, although the Conſent of the King and the Peers be not had there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</hi> 4. That <hi>to raiſe Arms againſt the Peoples Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives, is High-Treaſon.</hi> Thus were theſe Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Principles <hi>Previous</hi> and <hi>Preparative</hi> for that Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid <hi>Murder,</hi> which, to the Diſhonour of Nature, to the Reproach of Religion, to the Shame of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and to the Scandal of all Nations, was ſo bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſly committed on this Day. The <hi>Charge</hi> againſt that Incomparable Prince ran in the Name of the <hi>People;</hi> He had violated that <hi>Truſt</hi> which the <hi>People</hi> had repoſed in Him. Which thing when an Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Lady that was preſent Heard, ſhe cried out open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before the whole Court, It was a Lie, for not the <hi>Tenth</hi> part of the People would be guilty of ſuch a Crime. When the King demanded, by what <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> they brought Him to Tryal, that moſt <hi>Impudent</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt</hi> Judge, the <hi>Blaſphemer</hi> of God and His Anointed, anſwered, That 'twas by the Authority of the <hi>People.</hi> When the King had Solidly and Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently <hi>refuted</hi> that Pretence, that <hi>Monſter</hi> of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind <hi>perſiſted</hi> in it, That the <hi>People</hi> of <hi>England</hi> were the <hi>Supreme Authority</hi> of the Nation, over <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Laws</hi> too; that he was an Officer in <hi>Truſt,</hi> and that having broken his <hi>Compact</hi> with the <hi>People,</hi> they might juſtly proceed againſt Him, even unto Death: And this he endeavoured to prove by <hi>Arguments</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples,</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:93420:19"/>
all taken <hi>one</hi> by <hi>one</hi> out of the Counterfeit <hi>Doleman,</hi> which I mentioned before.</p>
            <p>Thus did theſe Treaſonable <hi>Principles</hi> coſt that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Monarch,</hi> firſt his <hi>Peace,</hi> and at laſt his <hi>Life,</hi> to the Eternal warning as well of every Upright <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate,</hi> that he preſume not to <hi>Suffer,</hi> as of every Faithful <hi>Subject</hi> that he preſume not to <hi>Liſten to</hi> thoſe Curſed <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Doctrines,</hi> which were never <hi>Formed</hi> and <hi>Deſigned</hi> but for <hi>Blood,</hi> were never <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced</hi> and <hi>Cheriſh'd</hi> but for <hi>Blood,</hi> were never <hi>Obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> and <hi>Followed</hi> but by Men, that Longed and Thirſt for Blood <hi>Royal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have no more to add, but my Humble and Hearty Prayers to the God of Order and Power, That he would Pardon that Great Sin which this day was act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt Himſelf and his Anointed, and Bleſs his Preſent Majeſty, and the whole Royal Family, with a long continuance of Life, Health, Peace, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; and that the courſe of this World may be ſo peaceably ordered by his Governance, that his Church may joyfully ſerve him in all Godly Quietneſs, through Jeſus Chriſt the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords; To whom with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, be all Honour and Glory World without end,</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
